Finding aid to the Sophia Smith papers. CA.MS.00004
Smith College Archives
Sophia Smith papers
1861 - 2001
Smith College Archives
Smith, Sophia, 1795 - 1870
CA.MS.00004
4.833 linear feet (12 containers)
Benefactor. Contains books, correspondence, journals, photographs, and personal and property records.
Biographical / Historical
Sophia Smith, benefactor of Smith College, was born in Hatfield, MA on August 27, 1796. She was the fourth of seven children of Joseph Smith, a prosperous farmer, and his wife, Lois White Smith. Of the seven Smith offspring, three died young and only Joseph Jr. married, producing no heirs. Sophia, her sister Harriet and brother Austin shared the family homestead which still stands at 22 Main Street in Hatfield.
Harriet Smith's death in 1859, followed by Austin's in 1861, left Sophia a wealthy woman attempting to make provisions for the Smith family fortune. Deeply religious, Sophia turned to her pastor, John Morton Greene, as well as other advisers, to discuss her options. Considered were bequests to Amherst College (Reverend Greene's alma mater) and to the nearby Mount Holyoke Female Seminary.
Initially, Sophia settled on a variety of projects, including a school for the deaf, a logical choice in light of her own struggles with impaired hearing. Thus, Smith College may, at least in part, owe its very existence to the fact that John Clarke died before she did, endowing a school for the deaf (the Clarke School in Northampton) and prompting Sophia to abandon her plan.
Sophia Smith died on June 12, 1870. The "Last Will and Testament of Miss Sophia Smith" was completed in March of 1870, nine years after her first meeting about the matter with John Greene. This final version supported "the establishment and maintenance of an institution for the higher education of young women, with the design to furnish for my own sex means and facilities for education equal to those which are afforded now in our Colleges to young men."
The will went on to state: "It is my opinion that by the education of women, what are called their 'wrongs' will be redressed, their wages adjusted, their weight of influence in reforming the evils of society will be greatly increased, as teachers, as writers, as mothers, as members of society, their power for good will be incalculably enlarged...It is my wish that the institution be so conducted, that during all coming time it shall do the most good to the greatest number. I would have it a perennial blessing to the country and the world."
[from Sophia Smith's vision: "A perennial blessing to the country and the world"]
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of her personal journal from 1861 to 1870, original correspondence to Mary Lyon Bliss, family papers and memorabilia including deeds and pew rent information, photographs, printed biographical and genealogical material, information about the Smith homestead in Hatfield, MA and volumes from her home library.
Arrangement
The Sophia Smith Papers are composed of seven (7) series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Correspondence
III. Journals
IV. Memorabilia
V. Photographs
VI. Publications about Hatfield
VII. Personal Library
Series I: Biographical Material contains newspaper clippings, publications, photographs, copies of deeds, Smith Family genealogy, copies of Sophia Smith's will, and information about the Smith Homestead in Hatfield, MA. The materials range in date from 19th century to the present.
Series II: Correspondence contains a letter to Mary Lyon Bliss, dated April 4, 1866.
Series III: Journals (1861-1870) consist of journals documenting Sophia Smith's thoughts and personal reflections, mostly of a religious nature, as she struggles with the second half of her life.
Series IV: Memorabilia contains pamphlets, a copy of a sampler by Sophia Smith, and other ephemera documenting Smith's role in establishing Smith College.
Series V: Photographs contains a small number of known images of Sophia Smith.
Series VI: Publications about Hatfield include the centennial history of the town and documents the role of the Smith Family in the community.
Series VII: Personal Library contains a selection of volumes from the Smith family household with publication dates ranging from 1810 until 1870.
Conditions Governing Access
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials in the Sophia Smith papers were donated by members of the John M. Green family as well as by interested alumnae over time.
Related Materials
For additional information about the founding of Smith College please consult:
RG 10. John M. Greene papers
RG 30. Laurenus Clark Seelye papers
Smith History Digital Collections
Hatfield (Mass.) -- History -- Sources; Smith, Sophia, 1796-1870 -- Will; Smith College -- History -- Sources; Smith College -- endowments
- Series I: Biographical Material
  - Collections Listing (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Albums with Sophia Smith signatures (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Booklist (from Homestead) (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Centennial and other Anniversaries (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Centennial: Photographs (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Centennial: Publications (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Deafness (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Genealogy: general (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Genealogy: oversized (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Genealogy: deeds and pew rents (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Genealogy: pew rents (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Genealogy: photographs (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Genealogy: Smith, Austin (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Genealogy: Smith, Joseph (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - Genealogy: Smith, Oliver (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Genealogy: publication Oliver Smith, Esquire (Box 24, Folder 16)
  - Genealogy: wills (Box 24, Folder 17)
  - Genealogy: Smith Charities, Inc. (Box 24, Folder 18)
  - Hatfield, Massachusetts (Box 24, Folder 19)
  - Hatfield, MA: photographs (Box 24, Folder 20)
  - Sophia Smith Homestead (Box 25, Folder 21)
  - Sophia Smith Homestead: Chintz (Box 25, Folder 22)
  - Sophia Smith Homestead: Photographs (Box 25, Folder 23)
  - Sophia Smith Homestead: Sampler (Box 25, Folder 24)
  - Sophia Smith Homestead: House built in 1865 (Box 25, Folder 25)
  - Printed Matter, general (Box 25, Folder 26)
  - Ring (Box 25, Folder 27)
  - Wills (Box 25, Folder 28)
  - Sophia Smith Window (Box 25, Folder 29)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Mary Lyon Bliss, 04/04/1866 (Box 25, Folder 30)
- Series III: Journals
  - Journals, 1861 - 1870 (Box 27)
  - Typescript of Journal (Box 26)
  - Transcript with annotations of Journal of Sophia Smith by John M. Greene (Box 29)
- Series IV: Memorabilia
  - General (Box 25, Folder 31)
  - 19th & 20th century materials (Box 25, Folder 32)
- Series V: Photographs
  - Photographs (Box 24, Folder 33)
  - Photographs (Box 24, Folder 34)
- Series VI: Publications about Hatfield
  - Publications About Hatfield (missing 10/30/18 - folder 35)
  - Publications About Hatfield (missing 10/30/18 - folder 36)
- Series VII: Personal Library
  - A Comprehensive View of the Leading and Most Important Principles of Natural and Revealed Religion, 1815 (Box 29.1)
  - A Compendium on the System of Divine Truth, 1824 (Box 29.1)
  - Conversations on Chemistry, 1820 (Box 29.1)
  - Thaddeus of Poland, 1817 (Box 29.1)
  - A Compendium of Pysiology and Systematic Botany, 1820 (Box 29.2)
  - Sabbath Hymn Book, 1858 (Box 29.2)
  - Barnes' Family Prayers, 1863 (Box 29.2)
  - Little Women, 1870 (Box 29.3)
  - The Plays of William Shakespeare, volume I, 1824 (Box 29.3)
  - Holy Bible, 1859 (Box 29.3)
  - Kardoo, the Hindoo Girl, 1869 (Box 29.4)
  - The Corner Stone, 1834 (Box 29.4)
  - Thaddeus of Warsaw, volume III, 1817 (Box 29.4)
  - Morrisons' Strangers' Guide and Etiquette for Washington City, 1864 (Box 29.4)
  - The Plays of William Shakespeare, volume II, 1824 (Box 29.4)
  - The Happy Choice, 1847 (Box 29.5)
  - The Still Hour, 1860 (Box 29.5)
  - Adjutant Steams, 1862 (Box 29.5)
  - The Young Christian Directed, 1854 (Box 29.5)
  - A Place in the Memory, 1851 (Box 29.5)
  - Atlantic Monthly (1864-1865) (Box 23a)
  - Personal Copies (Box 23b)